No. 42 – Configuration Management

As with many safety and quality practices, configuration management is often most visible by its absence.

As in…

What do you mean, you can’t find the source code?

Or…

You know that nasty bug we discovered last week?

Well, that’s been fixed now.

Unfortunately, we’ve also somehow lost the last three enhancements we made.

While the following list of suggested CM practices is not exhaustive, it’s a good place to start.

Make sure you have multiple backups of your source code – in development as well as in production.

Use a version control system that automatically maintains prior versions of all of your programs and modules.

For each release of your application, maintain a complete list of all the application’s components, with the version level of each.

Always create executables to be released via an automated build process using configuration-controlled source code.

Maintain records that always allow you to trace back from any given change in the source code to the original request that provided the rationale for the change.

Always maintain some separation of duties (SoD) between the developers and the folks responsible for implementing a release to production.

Words from Others on this Topic

Chris seems excited. “Brent, if it’s okay with you and everyone else, I’d like to invite you to our team sprints, so that we can get environment creation integrated into the development process as early as possible. Right now, we focus mostly on having deployable code at the end of the project. I propose we change that requirement. At each three-week sprint interval, we not only need to have deployable code but also the exact environment that the code deploys into, and have that checked into version control, too.”

– Gene Kim and Kevin Behr and George Spafford, The Phoenix Project: A Novel About IT, DevOps, and Helping Your Business Win, 2013

No. 13 – Consider Alternatives

Developers are often quick to use designs and patterns they are already familiar with, to try the first idea that occurs to them, and to persist with things that seem to be working.

However, the resulting product can often be made stronger through judicious consideration of alternatives early in the development process.

When generating alternatives, it’s good to get input from a broad range of people with varying backgrounds and perspectives. These alternatives can then be vetted through discussion, research and, often, some degree of quick prototyping.

Morgan and Liker have described one such approach as “set-based concurrent engineering,” and have pointed out that better and ultimately more workable designs are often developed by starting with broader sets of possible solutions, and then gradually converging on a final design.

Note that this approach requires a higher tolerance for a longer period of uncertainty early in the project, as alternative ideas are generated, evaluated and compared, but then results in less risk of having to rework the design late in the project, in order to accommodate issues that were not given sufficient consideration early on.

Since this approach results in spending more design time up front, but then less time re-designing later in the project, it is sometimes referred to as “front-loading the development process.”

Of course, any consideration of alternatives will require open and spirited discussion of the pros and cons of each. Such discussions can get messy, but these sorts of discussions are absolutely essential in order to achieve the best possible results.

Words from Others on this Topic

A critical aspect of all engineering disciplines is the elaboration of multiple approaches, trade-off analyses among them, and the eventual adoption of one. After requirements are agreed upon, you must examine a variety of architectures and algorithms.

– Alan M. Davis, 201 Principles of Software Development, 1995

No. 26 – Developers are Always Growing

Software developers are always learning new languages, frameworks, techniques and practices, and they are always getting better at those they have already started to learn. Such continual growth is made possible, as well as necessary, by the unremitting pace of growth in the field. In essence, there is no such thing as staying in the same place for very long – if you are not growing, then you are falling behind.

This idea of continual growth may at first sound like an empty platitude, but it actually leads directly to a number of critical insights.

First, it further explains why Developers Are Not Interchangeable.

Second, it provides an avenue for developers to pursue mastery, one of the three essential elements for developer engagement. (if you have a developer who is not growing, but is simply doing the same things they have been doing for some time, and doing them at the same level, then that is a problem that needs to be corrected, for this invariably means that such a developer has disengaged from his or her craft.)

Third, if we accept the Dreyfus Model of Skill Acquisition, this idea helps us understand why developers at different levels have completely different needs and tolerances for prescriptive organizational rules. For more on this topic, see the Pagan Tuna post, “The Dreyfus Model of Skill Acquisition.”

Fourth, and perhaps most profoundly, the implication for an organization is that the purpose of each new work assignment is not just to get the work done, but to help the assigned developers further their growth. In essence, this means that, for each development project, you have two goals to think about: a new or improved piece of software, and an improved set of software developers.

In order to ensure that developers are growing, it’s important for leadership to allow them adequate time to explore, learn and try new things, which means finding an appropriate balance between short-term productivity and longer terms goals of organizational growth. In general, it’s reasonable to expect that developers will spend 5 - 20% of their time – day after day, week after week – in some form of learning not directly required by their immediate job assignments.

Another important element of developer growth is to form teams with diverse skill sets and levels of expertise, so that developers can learn from one another as part of their work assignments.

No. 43 – Limit Work in Progress

In many software development environments, new requests seem to continually arrive in an uncontrolled fashion. The result can often be that work on the latest request interrupts completion of work that arrived earlier, so that all requests tend to take longer to complete, and the total amount of work-in-progress (WIP) increases, making it exponentially more difficult to manage.

Such an uncontrolled intake process also tends to reduce overall developer productivity, since developers spend more time task switching, and less time actually doing productive development.

This is why it is generally critical to limit the entry of new requests into an active in-work state. There are various approaches to implementing such limits, but one of them should generally be adopted in any active development environment.

One approach is to set specific numeric limits on the number of items that can be in work at any point in time, so that new items are started only as other items are completed.

When implementing such a system, it’s useful to plan for some sort of surge capacity, to handle emergent high-severity bugs, and it’s also useful to allocate certain percentages of your capacity to types of work other than new features for your customers – things like refactoring, defect correction, and reduction of technical debt – since otherwise items like these may have trouble competing successfully with new feature requests.

People who often change their minds

He [Jeff Bezos] said people who were right a lot of the time were people who often changed their minds. He doesn’t think consistency of thought is a particularly positive trait. It’s perfectly healthy — encouraged, even — to have an idea tomorrow that contradicted your idea today.

He’s observed that the smartest people are constantly revising their understanding, reconsidering a problem they thought they’d already solved. They’re open to new points of view, new information, new ideas, contradictions, and challenges to their own way of thinking.

This doesn’t mean you shouldn’t have a well formed point of view, but it means you should consider your point of view as temporary.

What trait signified someone who was wrong a lot of the time? Someone obsessed with details that only support one point of view. If someone can’t climb out of the details, and see the bigger picture from multiple angles, they’re often wrong most of the time.

– Jason Fried, “Some advice from Jeff Bezos: Signal vs. Noise”, 2018

No. 3 – The Inconvenient Nature of Software Development

Software development is often viewed from two completely different mindsets.

Let’s consider first the assumptions made by what we might call…

The Predictive Planning Model

Software development is best managed as a set of projects, with each project starting and ending at specific points in time.

There exists a finite set of requirements for any software development project.

That finite set of requirements is discoverable within some reasonable period of time.

That set of requirements can be accurately documented and validated before any working software is produced or executed.

Requirements are most usefully considered in a pure state, untainted by any traces of design.

The clearest way to communicate requirements is through written documents containing some combination of text and diagrams.

Requirements can be reliably validated through careful review of this documentation.

Customers can be relied upon to accurately identify the relative priorities of their requirements.

It is possible to define a repeatable process for requirements discovery, based on the principles above.

The goal of design is to satisfy all the requirements.

It is very expensive and risky to change software once it is coded and working, so it is critical to get the requirements and the design right before coding is allowed to begin.

At some point in the project early enough to be useful for purposes of planning and governance, the amounts of time and effort that will be required to complete the project can be accurately estimated.

As with other engineering disciplines, software engineering is based on a stable foundation of immutable laws.

It is possible to accurately gauge the overall progress of a project by collating and summarizing progress data from project team members.

Projects based on these principles will tend to produce satisfied customers.

These principles sound reasonable, don’t they? What’s more, they cohere nicely, coming together to form a picture of software development that seems pleasingly rational and predictable.

Wouldn’t it be nice if they were actually true?

However, many view software development from a completely different mindset.

Let’s call this one…

The Adaptive Model

Useful software products evolve rapidly and more or less continuously, so defining a “project” as a series of development activities with definite start and end dates is typically somewhat arbitrary, and often misleading.

Software requirements are a matter of opinion, and are therefore subjective, largely unbounded, always incomplete, and open to perpetual redefinition and reinterpretation.

Requirements documents for software development efforts of any significant size are generally difficult to understand and interpret consistently, and so offer an entirely misleading sense of control over the software coding activities to follow.

The supposed boundaries between requirements, design and coding are entirely porous, with all three “phases” of development interacting with and influencing the others.

Prioritizing requirements is generally difficult, since every requirement is important to someone, and no one wants to call another’s child ugly.

The cost of making software changes has consistently declined, due to the increasing power and sophistication of the languages and tools available to modern developers. And so writing software and then changing it based on reactions from stakeholders is often more efficient than going through elaborate and unreliable paper-based rituals prior to coding.

Any software development effort is either a journey of discovery, or a waste of resources. Either you are creating something new, or you are recreating something that’s already been done. If you are creating something new, then you had best be honest that you aren’t entirely sure what you’re doing, or how long it will take, until you’ve done it. If you’re entirely sure of what you’re going to do and when you’re going to do it, then you’re not developing something, you’re just putting a fresh coat of paint on something that already existed.

All software applications are built on top of hardware and software platforms that are themselves highly complex and still rapidly evolving. There are no limitations. There are no hard and fast rules. Everything is malleable, and everything is possible. In this sort of environment, it is folly to try to define some sort of repeatable and stable engineering discipline.

The demonstration of working software is the only reliable indicator of progress in any sort of software development activity. All other avowals of project progress are illusory.

Customers are happiest when the software is adaptive and evolving quickly in response to their explicit and implicit wants and needs.

Quite a different perspective, isn’t it?

Reality

The Predictive Planning Model is the one usually favored by leadership, because it portrays the act of writing software as a more or less trivial activity that can be easily and effectively managed from on high.

The Adaptive Model, on the other hand, is the one usually favored by developers, because it generally takes those annoying managers out of the picture and allows the developers to do what they do best without any pesky cost or schedule constraints.

So which of these is true?

Well, the inconvenient truth is that they both are, to varying degrees.

As I’ll argue shortly, Software Development is a Balancing Act.

Although it would be nice to believe that the Predictive Planning Model can be made to work, and although it has worked, for some, to some degree, under very special conditions, it cannot be really said to be true in general. Like Newtonian physics, it can sometimes give us a useful approximation of reality, but we will get ourselves in trouble if we rely on it to be absolutely valid under all conditions.

The Adaptive Model is generally much more realistic, until we run up against the problems of limited time, money and resources, because no organization that I’ve ever seen can really live with a development team that is constantly adapting to emergent conditions without being willing to give some reasonably reliable predictions of when it will be done meeting some important goal, and at what cost.

So where does that leave us?

If we are now left with the uncomfortable feeling that we have two different models, both of which can be helpful at times, but neither of which can be absolutely relied upon, then we are probably in the right place to begin thoughtful and appreciative consideration of Software Development’s other Big Ideas.

Words from Others on this Topic

…you said you think you know some things. What you mean is, you’ve constructed simplified representations of how those things work. But don’t confuse yourself by thinking your simplified mental constructions are realistic, or worse yet, true … Nothing useful is real. If it’s complicated enough to be realistic, it’s too complicated to be useful. That’s why we build models. Representations. When we say we know things, we just mean we have mental models of those things that we like. Often we like them because they’ve been useful. But let’s not confuse having a useful model with actual knowing.

Managers have a problem … when they fall in love with a particular model of how something works. When they become convinced that a mental model they have of how something works is the right one. When they decide that they know something. … when we become too wedded to a model, we lose our ability to deal with new situations.

– Robert D. Austin Richard L. Nolan and Shannon O’Donnell, Adventures of an IT Leader, 2009

No. 18 – Understand the Arc of Your Project

Software development has traditionally been thought of as proceeding through a series of phases. This is sometimes described as a Systems Development Life Cycle (SDLC), and is often managed via a series of gates that control progress from one phase to another, ensuring that the work of one phase has been completed successfully before allowing work on the next phase to start.

A fairly typical list of phases might be as follows:

Initiation
Requirements
Design
Construction
Testing
Implementation
Maintenance

Agile approaches, on the other hand, tend to break a project down into a series of time-boxed sprints or iterations, overlapping and compressing phases 2 - 6 (Requirements through Implementation) within each iteration. If there is any acknowledgment of a larger project lifecycle, it often consists merely of an initial iteration, referred to as iteration 0, dedicated briefly to startup tasks before beginning the actual work of coding in iteration 1.

In my experience, both of these approaches tend to have problems. The SDLC approach often tries to adhere too rigidly to firm gates, and often tends towards micromanagement in its review of deliverables needed to pass through each gate, losing sight of the forest in its minute review of the trees.

Watts Humphrey noted this first problem in trying to establish a firm conclusion to the requirements phase:

A common misperception is that we must start with firm requirements. There is a widespread but fallacious view that requirements are the customers’ job and that development should not start until they are explicitly defined. The fact is that the demand for firm and unchanging requirements is mostly wishful thinking….

– Watts Humphrey, Managing the Software Process, 1998

The Agile approach, on the other hand, often suffers because it assumes too blithely that all problems can be worked out during development iterations, with little up-front analysis and design work. As a result, I’ve heard frustrated executives declare that Agile is “just a way of producing crap faster.”

Unfortunately, many software development shops tend to cycle back and forth between these two approaches, favoring one or the other based on whichever one most recently yielded disappointing results. And a series of project failures based on both approaches often leaves in its wake two teams of firmly entrenched methodology advocates, endlessly battling over which of their approaches represents the truth and the light.

Models that try to get the best of both worlds are now commonly referred to as “scaled agile.” Two such examples are Dean Leffingwell’s Scaled Agile Framework (SAFe) and Scott Ambler’s Disciplined Agile Delivery (DAD) model. All of these scaled agile approaches have something to offer, and can help an organization move beyond the endless Agile vs. Traditional debates. For more on this topic, see the Pagan Tuna post “Benefits of the Scaled Agile Framework.”

However something important often gets lost in all of these attempts to reduce the reality of software development into the artificial confines of one model or another: the overall arc of your project.

What do I mean by this phrase?

Instead of a software development project, let’s think for a minute about something else that has a beginning, a middle and an end.

Let’s think about a book-length work of fiction: a novel.

We can think of each chapter of a novel as comparable to an iteration in an agile development project: each chapter delivers some additional dialogue, some additional characterization, and some additional elements of the plot, just as each iteration delivers some working software. And each chapter is roughly the same length as the others, just as each development iteration is often time-boxed into a prescribed length.

However, even though most of us wouldn’t consciously mark the progress of a novel from one phase into another, we all have an instinctive understanding that a book is not an unending series of chapters, that as the story unfolds, we are proceeding along a narrative arc that should eventually bring us to a satisfying conclusion. And if that arc is interrupted, or perverted – as it was very intentionally in Hitchcock’s movie Psycho, for example – then we feel that something is wrong, we may even be shocked, without the need to resort to a particular model of narrative fiction in order to reach that conclusion.

Now even though we don’t consciously think about these narrative stages as we’re reading a novel – and even though authors don’t always consciously consider them as they’re writing one – we can construct various models of how a story typically proceeds. There are, for example, the twelve stages of a hero’s journey, as identified by Joseph Campbell. Or we could look at the five act structure used explicitly in many plays. For our purposes today, though, let’s just consider the simplest of these, the three act structure.

Act I – Used for exposition, to establish the main characters, their relationships, the worlds they live in and, finally, the problem to be solved.

Act II – Our hero wrestles with the problem, encountering setbacks along the way, and gradually discovers new resources to help address the central problem.

Act III – The problem is resolved.

Let’s return now to consideration of the nature of a software development project. If we think broadly about the structure of any such project, I will submit that we can typically discern three distinct “acts,” even though they will typically overlap and not be clearly delineated.

Discover: In the first phase, a project team is discovering all they can about the problem space, and about potential elements of a solution. Questions are mostly open-ended, and you are working to get the general lay of the land.

Drive to Decisions: At this point the team has developed a good sense of what is expected of them, and their interests narrow to focus on some fairly specific concerns. Typically, these involve ambiguities in the problem space, competing perspectives held by different stakeholders, or difficult design trade-offs. Resolving these issues generally requires some tough decisions to be made.

Deliver: Finally, when they get those open issues nailed down, the team knows with some precision what they need to do, and they marshal the troops to go off and deliver on the promises made to their customers.

Note that working software can be developed and delivered in all three of these acts, although the purposes of this development will be somewhat different for each, in line with the varying characterizations given above. Note also that this three-act structure may be repeated within the larger arc of a sizable project, if delivery of overall project objectives has been decomposed into a series of somewhat smaller efforts (just as it is repeated in fiction within a trilogy).

How does this three-act structure for software development help us?

First, we should note that the key mindsets necessary to succeed are very different in these three acts. If I may be allowed to use some canine analogies:

The Discover act primarily requires boundless curiosity – much the same thing my Golden Retriever exhibits when he is let off his leash in a new space. You need to run around in all directions at once, discovering and testing boundaries, sniffing anything that might be interesting.

In the Drive to Decisions act, though, you need to be more focused and persistent, doing whatever it takes to resolve your significant remaining issues. In this phase you are more like a bloodhound, relentlessly following the scent of its quarry.

In the Deliver act, you need to be efficient and steady in making progress towards the finish line. You have lots of stuff to do, you know what it is, and you need to go about doing it. At this point, what you need is a sheepdog, rounding up the flock and bringing them home at day’s end, making sure that no straggler gets lost.

Next, we can note that many project failures are traceable back to a problem of giving too much or too little attention to one or more of these acts.

Some projects get stuck in perpetual Discovery mode, wandering around for months and even years without ever figuring out what it is they’re supposed to do.

Some projects skip the Drive to Decisions phase, sweeping all the difficult decisions under the rug in the vain hope that they will somehow sort themselves out later. As Joel Spolsky has noted:

In too many programming organizations, every time there’s a design debate, nobody ever manages to make a decision, usually for political reasons. So the programmers only work on uncontroversial stuff. As time goes on, all the hard decisions are pushed to the end. These projects are the most likely to fail.

– Joel Spolsky, Joel on Software, 2004

And then there are the projects that try to go straight to the Deliver act in a misguided effort to complete faster.

Once you begin to develop a sense of what these three acts look like, and how they work, then it becomes easier to detect and correct project narratives that are deviating from what is likely to be a successful arc. (Although it should perhaps be noted that it may be easier for an English major to apply this wisdom than it is for someone trained in traditional project management disciplines.)

One document that can help a project navigate through these three acts successfully is a list of questions or open issues. I’m not talking about issues in a project management sense, since these are typically viewed as things that are threatening the normal progression of the project. I’m just talking about the normal list of questions that typically arise during any development project. This is typically a document that would be used by a development team or an analyst or an architect or a team lead, not by a project manager, and would not be managed with any degree of formality or management oversight.

And I’m not suggesting that this list need replace any of a project’s other documents; often the answers to all these questions will ultimately get recorded in other documents that may be of a more permanent nature.

Here is how such a list would be used in each of these three acts.

Discover: At the beginning of this act, you won’t yet know enough to even formulate such a list, but should have the goal of being able to start such a list. By the end of this act, you should have a fairly comprehensive and specific list of open questions that need answers.

Drive to Decisions: As you try to answer the questions you have listed, you will come up with some answers, as well as some further questions. Record the answers (which can also be characterized as decisions that have been made), as well as the additional questions, and move the answered questions down into a lower section of the list. In some cases, developing some quick software prototypes to show your customers may be the best way to get solid answers to some of your questions. You may also want to make note of the reasons for particular decisions. When you’ve got a long list of answered questions, and only minor issues left to be resolved, and the pace of adding additional questions has slowed or stopped, you’re at the end of Act II.

Deliver: Now start or continue the steady delivery of working software, based on the answers you’ve come up with. As additional questions arise, don’t panic or try to sweep them under the rug, just continue to add them to the list and get answers to them. Similarly, if the answers to some questions change, just make sure everyone is in agreement with the new answer, record it, and proceed to deliver.

If we focus on the details of a project, then we will often see subplots, red herrings, surprises, suspense and mystery, just as we do in any good novel. After all, any software development project is fundamentally a journey of discovery: our intent is always to discover the big things early on, and have fewer and smaller surprises as we continue, but any omniscience we can claim is only in hindsight. If we’re trying to track progress according to a traditional project plan, then the project may appear to be in a state of chaos.

If we step back and look at the overall arc of the project, though, proceeding through the three acts of Discover, Drive to Decisions, and Deliver, then we can often get a much better sense of whether a project is fundamentally on track or headed off the road and into the weeds. And a list of open questions, paired with a list of closed questions and their answers, can help key leaders navigate the roiling waters of any challenging project, ultimately leading their teams and stakeholders to a successful conclusion.

Words from Others on this Topic

As Bill Janeway said to me, it seems that Jeff [Bezos] “wanted rich discussion up front leading to Decision Time and then highly structured communication during Execution Time.”

– Jeff Bezos, as recounted by Bill Janeway, and as quoted by Tim O’Reilly in WTF?: What’s the Future and Why It’s Up to Us, 2017

No. 35 – When Estimating, the Whole is Definitely Greater than the Sum of its Parts

The time needed to complete an entire project will always be greater than the sum of the estimates for completing the individual tasks.

Why?

Some necessary tasks will not be included in your detailed estimates.

Estimates are usually based on the assumption that things will go well, and they often don’t.

The time needed for communication and coordination is probably not included, and this work often increases exponentially as the entire project team size increases.

The time needed for requirements collection and analysis, design, testing and governance/compliance activities is often missing, or understated.

The time needed to bring new team members up to speed is often not included.

Significant productivity differences between developers are often not taken into account.

One way to deal with this problem is to add some additional reserve to the project budget that is under management control. This might generally be referred to as the Management Reserve (MR).

In some environments, there might be a distinction between contingency reserves that are established to address specific risks already identified, vs. a more general management reserve held back to address situations that have not yet been foreseen. Using the terminology popularized by Donald Rumsfeld, these might be used, respectively, for the “known unknowns” and the “unknown unknowns.”